Guide to the Leonard Strong Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Leonard Strong collection
1923-1961
GEN MSS 1084
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.71
(10 boxes)
The Leonard Strong Collection consists of autograph manuscripts and typescripts of poems, essays, short stories, and monographs; correspondence; and drawings by Strong which were acquired by the library over several decades. A group of materials acquired from James T. Babb include his correspondence with Strong and the book and manuscript dealer Bertram Rota.
Strong, L. A. G. (Leonard Alfred George), 1896-1958
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James T. Babb, 1965; purchased from G. F. Sims on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1973; and acquired from unidentified sources.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Leonard Strong (1896-1958)
Leonard Alfred George Strong was an English writer of essays, novels, poetry, history, and other works. He was a director of Methuen Ltd. publishers from 1938 until 1958. Green Memory, Strong's autobiography, was published by Methuen Ltd. in 1961.
Scope and Contents
The Leonard Strong Collection consists of autograph manuscripts and typescripts of poems, essays, short stories, and monographs; correspondence; and drawings by Strong which were acquired by the library over several decades. A group of materials acquired from James T. Babb include his correspondence with Strong and the book and manuscript dealer Bertram Rota.
A folder of catalog cards and lists for the Leonard Strong Collection is filed in box 1.
Arrangement
Organized in three groupings: I. December 1965 Acquisition. II. August 1973 Acquisition. III. Undated Acquisitions.
Authors, English -- 20th Century; English literature -- 20th Century; Manuscripts -- Collectors and collecting; Drawings (visual works) -- England -- 20th Century; Authors -- England -- 20th Century; Strong, L. A. G. (Leonard Alfred George), 1896-1958; Babb, James T. (James Tinkham), 1899-1968; Bertram Rota Ltd
- December 1965 Acquisition, 1923-1961; 1; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Consists of James T. Babb's gift of Strong material which includes Babb's correspondence with Strong and his wife, Sylvia; Strong's outgoing correspondence with friends and colleagues; and manuscripts and typescripts of essays, poems, short stories, and notes. The material also includes Babb's correspondence with the dealer Bertram Rota, from whom he acquired his collection, and the artist J. Howard Lewis.
  - Leonard Strong Collection card catalogs and lists (Box 1)
  - James T. Babb correspondence
    - Lewis, J. Howard, 1931 (Box 1)
    - Rota, Bertram, 1936-1959, undated (Box 1)
    - Strong, Leonard, 1930-1958 (Box 1)
    - Strong, Sylvia (Mrs. Leonard Strong), 1958-1961 (Box 1)
  - Leonard Strong correspondence
    - Carter, Reverend W. Gordon, 1933-1935 (Box 1)
    - Cournos, John, 1923-1927 (Box 1)
    - Freeman, John, 1925-1926 (Box 1)
    - Gawsorth, John, 1932-1951 (Box 1)
    - Osborne, E. A., 1931-1937 (Box 1)
    - The Spectator, 1931 (Box 1)
    - Stott, Raymond Toole, 1934-1935 (Box 1)
    - Unidentified, 1924 June 9 (Box 1)
  - Leonard Strong pencil drawings, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Essays, poems, short stories, and notes
    - "At Glenam Cross: A Sequence", 1928 (Box 1)
    - Autobiographical essay, undated (Box 1)
    - "A [autobiographical] Note by L. A. G. Strong", undated (Box 1)
    - Broadcast introduction to the English Festival of Spoken Poetry, undated (Box 1)
    - "The Burial Race", undated (Box 1)
    - "Death of the Gardener", undated (Box 1)
    - "Don Juan and the Wheelbarrow", 1931 (Box 1)
    - "The Dressing Gown", undated (Box 1)
    - "Escapade Notes" [later titled Dewer Rides ], undated (Box 1)
    - Essay on George Darley, undated (Box 1)
    - "Going North", undated (Box 1)
    - "The Honeymoon Couple", 1931 (Box 1)
    - "Parsons, Parsons!", undated (Box 1)
    - "The Rook", undated (Box 1)
    - "The Tide", undated (Box 1)
    - "Twenty Minutes", undated (Box 1)
    - Writings on W. B. Yeats, undated (Box 1)
  - Book manuscripts
    - "Corporal Tune", undated (Box 2)
    - "Light Above the Lake", undated; 2 (Box 2)
    - Seven chapters of Strong's autobiography, undated (Box 2)
- August 1973 Acquisition, undated; 2; 0.42; (1 box)
  Consists of an autograph manuscript for Strong's first book, Dewer Rides, first published in London by V. Gollancz Ltd. in 1929.
  - "Dewer Rides", undated; 10 (Box 3)
- Undated Acquisitions, 1931, undated; 3; 1.66; (7 boxes)
  Consists of bound and unbound manuscripts and typescripts of essays and monographs.
  - Essays
    - "The Hansom Cab and the Pigeon: Random Reflections Upon the Silver Jubilee of King George the Fifth", undated (Box 4)
    - "A Letter to W. B. Yeats", 1931 (Box 4)
  - Unbound manuscripts and typescripts
    - "The Brothers", undated; 3 (Box 4)
    - "The Garden," autograph manuscript, undated; 4 (Box 4)
    - "The Garden," typescript with corrections, 1931; 5 (Box 5)
    - "The Jealous Ghost", undated; 5 (Box 5)
  - Bound manuscripts and typescripts
    - "The Big Man", [1930?] (Box 6)
    - "Corporal Tune", undated (Box 7)
    - "The Minstrel Boy", undated (Box 8)
    - "Sea Wall", undated (Box 9)
    - "The Seven Arms", undated (Box 10)